

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia December 2022

December 2022
□ +61 466 683 552 | ▼toddellis.wa@gmail.com | ○ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ■ Todd-Ellis-4 | ○ toddellis | □

tmichaelellis

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY.

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

University of Tasmania 2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Bellingham, WA, USA

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

San Marcos, TX, USA

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - present

- Developing statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managing design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- · Designing and implementing programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- · Overseeing development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - present

- · Developing complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- Overseeing multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- · Managing custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- · Collaborating with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Sustainability Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

2010 10 2021 02

2019-10 - 2021-02

2018-12 - 2019-05

- Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes
- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

• Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets

- Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets
- Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- · Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

Faculty Research Assistant

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

2017-11 - 2018-06

Wenatchee, WA, USA

- Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- · Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

Biological Science Technician II

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- · Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment

Ridgefield, WA, USA

2017-08 - 2017-11

CONSULTING

2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery

Frontier Development Lab

2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity

USDA Forest Service

2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate

USDA Forest Service

HONOURS

2022-11 Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research

Australian Museum

2021-09 Future Students Staff Excellence 2021 Sustainability Award

University of Tasmania

2021-08 Certifi-Cat of Appreciation

Ten Lives Cat Centre

2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)

NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub

2018-06 Best Fish and Wildlife Science

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

2017-10 Conservation Award

Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

Foster Parent Hobart, TAS, Australia

Ten Lives Cat Centre 2020-05 - present

Animal Handler

New Braunfels, TX, USA

Humane Society of the New Braunfels Area 2018-08 - 2019-01

Animal Handler Wenatchee, WA, USA

Wenatchee Valley Humane Society 2018-03 - 2018-08

Technology Tutor Wenatchee, WA, USA

North Central Regional Library 2018-01 - 2018-08

Geographic Information Systems TechnicianPortland, OR, USAPORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY2017-01 - 2017-11

TONICAND STATE ONIVERSITY

Assistant Librarian

Kelso, WA, USA

2017-01 - 2017-11